# Ruijia "Regina" Cheng

# **Qualitative & Quantitative UX researcher**

rcheng6@uw.edu | https://reginachangzhou.github.io

Ph.D. in Human-computer interaction (HCI). 6+ years of experience in qualitative and quantitative research on AI-powered programming, creativity and writing software, online communities, and education technology.

*Key Skills* Qualitative Research: interview, ethnography, usability testing, design probe, grounded theory, design workshops, thematic analysis, literature review | Quantitative Research: survey, A/B testing, experiment design, statistical modeling, inferential statistics, psychophysics | Programming: Python, R, SQL, MATLAB, JavaScript, web development (React, Node.js), machine learning (PyTorch), Unity | Design: Photoshop, Figma, Illustration, Blender

# **Selected Professional Experiences**

### Apple AI/ML Resident in Human Centered Machine Intelligence

07/2023 to present

- Led and collaborated in research about AI in data visualization, creativity support, and software development tools.
- Contributed to the development of internal tools and products. Published in broader academic communities.

# **University of Washington Graduate Researcher, HCI**

09/2018 to 06/2023

- Led 10+ formative and evaluative research projects and published research reports on top HCI venues. Topics include online peer production platforms, data science & programming tools, STEM education, and creativity support.
- Conducted 100+ interviews & 50+ user studies; analyzed activity log of 500k+ users using statistical methods.
- Designed and built data pipelines and user-facing web applications.
- Managed teams of 5-10 researchers and engineers, set agendas, and mentored junior researchers.

#### Microsoft Research HCI Research Intern, AI Software Development Tools

06/2022 to 09/2022

- Led a multi-phase research on user trust in AI-powered code generation tools; designed and conducted 30+ interviews & 20+ evaluative studies with software engineers; built visual prototypes to convey design insights.
- Generated research reports for engineering teams and disseminated findings in broader academic communities.
- Reported design insights to director-level stakeholders and GitHub Copilot product team.

# **Dataminr HCI Research Intern, Human-AI Collaboration in NLP**

09/2021 to 12/2021

- Led research on human-in-the-loop text summarization; synthesized 600+ academic literatures into design framework; developed Figma prototypes and conducted evaluative studies with crowd workers.
- Generated **research reports** for internal usage and **publications** in broader academic communities.
- Reported to director-level stakeholders and impacted the design of internal AI-powered tools.

#### Meta UX Research Intern, Video Recommendation

06/2020 to 09/2020

- Led 20k+ surveys in 5 countries, interviews, usability tests, and statistical analysis of 20k+ user logs.
- Impacted the design of recommendation algorithms and video players with insights from international markets.
- Collaborated effectively with cross-functional teams (engineering, design, PM, and data) and vendors.

#### **Education**

# University of Washington (UW) Doctor of Philosophy in Human Centered Design & Engineering 2023 Master of Science in Human Centered Design & Engineering 2021 University of California, San Diego (UCSD) Magna Cum Laude Bachelor of Science in Cognitive Science with a Specialization in Computation 2018 Bachelor of Science in Mathematics: Applied Science 2018

Last Updated: January 2024